<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Le Tombeau des controverses a grave for controversies, between the Romanist &amp; Protestant, lately presented to the King of France / Englished by M.M.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15915</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12280078</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12280078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58669</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62858)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58669)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 880:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Le Tombeau des controverses a grave for controversies, between the Romanist &amp; Protestant, lately presented to the King of France / Englished by M.M.</title>
                  <author>M. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Milbourn for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58669:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58669:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Le Tombeau des Controverſes;</hi> A GRAVE FOR Controverſies, Between the <hi>ROMANIST &amp; PROTESTANT,</hi> Lately Preſented to the KING of France.</p>
            <p>Engliſhed by <hi>M. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Allowance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Milbourn,</hi> for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Armes</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58669:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58669:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>EXperience hath taught me, that Authors are commonly injured by Tranſlators, which proceeds from their Ignorance ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and ſomtimes from their Careleſneſs and Neglect; how guilty ſoever I am of the firſt, I have made it my buſineſs to avoyd the latter. The Author has Writ in a generous and ſmooth Style; what you find rough and unpoliſhed (in this Verſion) I muſt own. I have given you the true Sence and Meaning of this <hi>French Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor,</hi> the <hi>Idiom</hi> and Propriety of the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage would not ſuffer me to turn it <hi>Verbatim,</hi> in many places.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58669:3"/>
            <p>I am ſenſible that I run the risk of being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and cenſured by every one that will take the pains to read both, and compare them; and I am as ſenſible that it is but common Charity to pardon my faults and eſcapes (if he finds any) ſince every ingenious man does ſo, almost to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Authour he reads; I reſt in the Confidence of your Candor.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58669:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Le Tombeau des Controverſes;</hi> A GRAVE for CONTROVERSIES, Between the <hi>Romaniſt</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Lately preſented to the King of <hi>France,</hi> Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>M. M.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know you love the frankneſs of your friends, and to give you a Teſtimony of mine, I beſeech you ſend me your free thoughts of the Union of the two Religions in <hi>France,</hi> which has been, and is ſtill, ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed.</p>
            <p>I make no excuſes for the trouble I am bold to give you; ſince I phancy, you are (in ſome ſort) obliged to me, for the task I im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon you.</p>
            <p>Your mind (which cannot live lazily and aſleep) in all it's ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, applys it ſelf ſo cheerfully and to ſuch noble Subjects, that thoſe who buſie you, think they oblige you; ſince by it, they doe ſervice to Vertue and Piety, both which you love.</p>
            <p>They talk that the King will no more ſuffer two Religions in his Empire; that he hath often ſaid, One King, one Faith, one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58669:4"/>Law; That he will order a Conference of ſome Doctors of each Religion, that he will command them to agree, and find an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for it; and when he has ſeen their Concluſions, will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Peace by an Act of Union ſet forth by his Majeſty; That the King will ſend an expreſs to Rome to obtain a liberty for this Conference; That he is an enemy to ſoveraign Arbitration, and, in ſhort, that he is reſolved to ſee all his Subjects live in the practice of one and the ſame Religion.</p>
            <p>This news hath given an Allarme to both parties; the Roman-Catholiques and the Reformed or Proteſtants are almoſt equally frighted at it: The Reformed fear leſt the King ſhould force them to follow thoſe things which they abhor, as ſome ſuperſtitions, ſo frightful to their Conſciences, and ſome errors ſo deſpiſed by their Reaſons, that t'is impoſſible they could ever conſent to them; and being conſtrained to mask their faith with the figures of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryſie, their Souls would ſuffer mortal ſadneſs and horrible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietudes: The Romans are tied, by cuſtom, to the external practice of their Devotion, and make it as well the glory of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as the comfort of their Souls: They fear leſt the King ſhould baniſh with ſcorn, many cuſtomes to which they are beſotted, and reject them as actions very uſeleſs to that real Piety, which conſiſts in the true light of the mind and righteous affections of the heart.</p>
            <p>The wiſer ſort have leſs terrour but are not leſs troubled with the thoughts of this Deſign; and becauſe they believe not this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe fully reſolved upon by his Majeſty, every one imagines ſome way how to break or bring it to paſs, as if the two parties were already upon the point of finding their ſatisfaction or deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction. As for me, I profeſs to you, my mind cannot find one thought which is fixed, upon a Subject of ſo high importance; hope and fear equally ſhare me, I beſeech you therefore to contribute towards the calming of theſe motions by letting me know your thoughts concerning it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:58669:4"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur freedome would have appeared more pleaſing if leſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming; but I have no advice to give you, you will receive as little of that in the moſt abſtruſe matters as in things of leſſer moment, ſince you expect light from my darkneſs, for your free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with me in matters ſo curious.</p>
               <p>Your mind will be ſurpriſed if you find any, and if you find none you will be juſtly puniſhed for your imprudent hopes; and for my ſelf I ſhall be highly revenged of you.</p>
               <p>My Anſwer will have many diſtinct Articles to make you appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend my thoughts with the clearer diſtinctions, and in the ſame order which I have conceived them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Uniting of all minds to believe the ſame Truths; is an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffect which proceeds but only from the firſt cauſe.</p>
               <p>God only is the Father of Spirits, not only in respect of his Creation but in regard alſo of his Soveraign Government; He is as well the abſolute maſter of it as of the Will, not to do violence to it, but to perſwade and make it free: It's true then, that he only is able to make all men have the ſame thoughts of Piety, as the Sun is only able to give Splendour to the Univerſe, when all the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral torches make diverſe lights in diverſe places, without ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceing one day.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I know that there are ſome unqueſtionable Truths which all men know and none can diſpute; In the firſt rank of theſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Truths is placed the Idea of a Sovereign Being, worthy Reſpect and Love.</p>
               <p>But to come to this point which properly makes the centre of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the Circumference of minds is ſo wide and ſtretched out, they have drawn ſo many croſſed and confuſed lines, that they have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58669:5"/>produced an infinity of diſtances, figures, and oppoſitions.</p>
               <p>In this multitude one may diſcern many lines which being drawn from the ſame point carry the eye and apprehenſion juſt to the Centre which is ſought for, all juſtly leading to an Union with God; they are different, they ſeem oppoſite, but all are united by the production of the ſame effect; They ſeem to repreſent the the Plat-form of a very regular Town, all whoſe ſtreets lead to the Church.</p>
               <p>But the corruption of men (which conſiſts of malice and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) have drawn lines ſo fooliſh and irregular, that they can never meet one another, nor lead to that quietude which right reaſon requires and which joynes mankind to God; theſe lines touch regular lines but only in croſſing them, and they even croſs one another; ſo, that t'is impoſſible that they ſhould meet in the ſame point, or ſhould lead to that which is the only juſt and true one.</p>
               <p>The dread of Soveraign Power, the conſideration of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of mankind, the love of the goodneſs of God, the eſteem of his juſtice, the admiration of his wiſe conduct, the meditation of his admirable providences, the hatred of our own wickedneſſes, the averſion from, or abhorrence of our faults, the grief for our paſt errours, the fears of approaching judgment; are divers reaſons, all which brings or leads us to God directly.</p>
               <p>But the adoration of Jdols or of creatures, under pretence that they repreſent or that they contain the grandeur of Divinity, the Sacrifice of things ſtolen or of humane blood, the affected cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which paſs as a law, (although little beloved by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) cuſtomary words or praiſes of God not joyned with a holy love, the practices which are eſtabliſhed and protected by the intereſt of ſome Authority, the gorgeous Ornaments to draw aſide and divert the thoughts of the people, and all the inventions which buſie the mind about ſenſual and material things, are irregularities which make us ſtray from true Pietie, though ſome people have been governed quietly by them.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58669:5"/>
               <p n="3">3. One cannot eaſily Imagine a humane Power capable to recal Men from the ſtraying Paths which they have taken or will take; the deſign of reducing them into a way that is good, is certainly, the task of one that muſt be both wiſe and abſolute; and for the execution of it, 'Tis neceſſary (methinks) that the underſtanding of that man ſhould be without any Clouds and Darkneſs, and his Authority without Limits.</p>
               <p>Private men have words to explain themſelves, Reaſon to enlighten others, Arguments to convince, and Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſufficient to perſwade, Soveraignes have Authority to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and Power to force people; but yet with all their <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines,</hi> 'tis very difficult or rather impoſſible to lead or drive men to <hi>Heaven</hi> by one and the Same Way; the difference of Natures, the diſpoſition of the Genius, Cuſtomes, Intereſts, and Concerns, outward Shews, Fears, the engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Honour and Friends cauſe ſuch ſtrange differences and diverſities in humane Souls, that all cannot be perſwaded into the ſame thoughts, nor touched with the ſame Reaſon.</p>
               <p>I know that the grand diverſity which we ſee in Nature, (which we know only by its Accidents) may be alſo found in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality and much more in Piety, becauſe but few know the true Eſſence of it. We cannot deny but all people apprehend and ſeek after the ſame God; but who can hinder that one and the ſame Figure ſhould repreſent ſeveral objects, according to its di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe poſitions and the ſeveral places in which the beholders are, or who ſhall hinder the Sun from framing that diverſity of repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation according to the diverſe Climates upon which it ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth?</p>
               <p>Many have ſhewed me their holy extravagancies ſpeaking confidently of the condition of the World before ſin had made it miſerable; they told me, that the ſeveral motions of the Sun would have produced neither Winter, Darkneſs, nor Death; that untill'd ground would have produced neither Brambles nor Thorns
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58669:6"/>nor any noiſome Plants; they had imaginations ſo finely orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that I could not deny giveing their Idea the Image of a world made of Miracles.</p>
               <p>I muſt believe that, but for the weakneſs, fantaſticalneſs, and wickedneſs of Man, we had known no defect in any Religion: But if we would re-eſtabliſh this happy Unity, (which is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of perfect innocency) there muſt follow two Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; an expulſion of Darkneſs and Malice from the mindes of all Men.</p>
               <p>The true Worſhip which is in Spirit and Truth, we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly find to be laid aſide by ignorant Teachers or malicious Builders; if we ſee Truth in the moſt conſiderable place of the Building, and if Truth does unite the two Walls at the point of the Angle which is the moſt regular, then we may ſing with the Prophet, God alone Almighty and only Wiſe hath done this thing before our Eyes, his hand alone hath done this work by this ſtrong and glorious Armes.</p>
               <p>The Princes who do or ſhall ſee this happineſs in their Lands, ought to ſay, this is the day which the Lord hath made.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If it be true that our King and Monarch deſires that there be but one Religion in his Kingdom, he deſires a very good thing; and no doubt the excellency of his diſpoſition, will make him propound and follow that way of Piety which is moſt agreeable to Reaſon and moſt Spiritual, and which the moſt generous and Chriſtian Soul would chuſe to unite it ſelf with God; mean fortunes are aimed at only by mean people, but the moſt Illuſtrious reach after Perfection.</p>
               <p n="5">5. All the Kings ſubjects who have rational Ingenuities, and Souls truly Pious ought to approve, follow, and cheriſh this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of his Majeſties, all ought to contribute to this heavenly Peace; a houſe muſt needs be full of trouble, if its inhabitants treat one another with cenſuring and fury and look upon one another with the Eyes of Enmity; I find nothing ſo troubleſome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58669:6"/>in life, as the neceſſity of liveing with thoſe men who Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach one another with equal Fierceneſs, as if their different thoughts in matters of Religion were abominable Crimes, and who look upon one another as Reprobates, enemies of God, ſervants of Satan, and deſtined to Damnation.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſad Emotions produce ſuch helliſh Hatreds and ſuch preſſing Sadneſſes in the weaker Party; they bring forth ſuch bloody Violences and cruel Inhumanities in the moſt powerful Party; that theſe infernal Reproaches make a kind of Hell, which torments the inhabitants of the ſame Countrey, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the ſame Prince, the children of the ſame Father, the neareſt relations in the ſame Family, the friendſhips of the moſt ſacred Alliances, every one ſets himſelf to curſe his Brother, and would willingly take the ſatisfaction of ruining him.</p>
               <p>I cannot think of this barbarous Zeal without ſighing, and without ſome Horror for theſe inhumane Men, who ceaſe to be Rational when they would be eſteemed Pious; muſt our cruelty paſs for a myſtery of Religion? our infamous Vices for the height of Vertue? muſt we our ſelves believe and perſwade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that to become good Angels we muſt act like Brutes?</p>
               <p>Sure if men would follow right Reaſon, they would reſolve to bear theſe different Opinions, (which gives Piety ſo many and ſo various Shapes) without Fury, Hatred, and Violence; certainly they would ſuffer with a prudent Patience, the errors of the Night, ſtill expecting that the Morning-ſtar, or the Sun it ſelf ſhould (in due time) diſcover all things with a true light.</p>
               <p>But who can hinder the furious madneſs of theſe bitter Spirits, who run down and conſume all that oppoſeth their Opinions? who can fix Notions in the weak Vulgar, who having nothing but a ſpirit of chaffe, or vapour, are hurried by the little winde that puffeth them.</p>
               <p>Minds ſo ill managed, make in the ſame Family (of which the King is the Maſter and Father) an army of <hi>Midianites</hi> who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58669:7"/>deſtroy each other, animating themſelves one againſt another, whil'ſt the darkneſs hinders them from knowing themſelves, and in a tumult too which will not permit them to be able to know one another. There is no need, (Dear <hi>Eutimius</hi>) to prove to you, that which you already know, nor to repreſent to you what you ſee already; you may conclude eaſily by the train of our Experiences, that if his Majeſty deſires one only Religion in <hi>France,</hi> he deſires a very good thing.</p>
               <p n="6">6. I cannot eaſily bear the Opinion of thoſe who endeavour to maintain that it doth not belong to Kings to intermeddle with Religion, as if Piety and Holineſs were not uſed by great Ones: This apprehenſion is Falſe, moſt Unjuſt and moſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious, it is the daughter of a wicked Politician, of an intereſted Cabal, or of down-right and crafty Tyrany.</p>
               <p>Then Kings ſuffer themſelves to be Cheated, when they are perſwaded that all that which has regard to Devotion is no part of their Empire, nor ſubjected to their Government. This Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime appeares very ſweet to thoſe who would render themſelves Monarchs over Kings by the pretences of Piety; the leaſt incroaching upon this matter ſtirs up, and animates their jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal of <hi>Perroun</hi> being yet but the Biſhop of <hi>Everuſe</hi> was in election to have publick conference with <hi>Du Pleſſis Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay;</hi> the Popes Nuntio Biſhop of <hi>Modena</hi> went to King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, and told him that this action of deputing Comiſſaries in the matters of Religion was of Eccleſiaſtique Authority; and he beſeeched his Majeſty not to be ſurpriſed at the requeſt which he made to him. The King contented him with aſſuring him, that no one ſhould treat of the Fundamentals of Religion, but of ſome little things only.</p>
               <p>Popes have never been more ſtirred up againſt the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, and conſequently againſt <hi>Ferdinand</hi> his brother and Succeſſor, then by the cares which they had taken to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58669:7"/>the Eſtranged ſentiments of Religion; the Roman court maintained that theſe vertuous deſigns were ranked among wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Enterpriſes and rebellious Raſhneſs.</p>
               <p>The ſhortneſs of a Letter will not ſuffer mee to write the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves of this Debate; I will only tell you ſomething of it, to ſatisfy mine own mind as well as yours. The firſt practiſes of the World let us ſee, that the heads of Families were the Princes and Prieſts of them; The two firſt ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> (who were Princes of the two great Families of the World) were both Prieſts, although by a ſecret of divine Providence that of <hi>Abel</hi> was extinguiſhed in his perſon, it was repaired by the birth of <hi>Seth,</hi> continued by <hi>Enoch,</hi> and by all thoſe who were named the race or children of God.</p>
               <p>After the ruine by the deluge, <hi>Noah</hi> remained Prince of his Family, did the office of a Preiſt, and before that ſevere ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of the flood he is repreſented to us as a Herauld of juſtice, who condemned the World by preaching againſt the wickedneſs of it.</p>
               <p>Was not <hi>Abraham</hi> Father, Prince, and Prieſt of his Family; he was found worthy to receive this praiſe in a ſtrange Land by the principal men of the Countrey, <hi>Thou art among us a Prince of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame Age the Prince of <hi>Salem</hi> bore the title <hi>Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck</hi> King of juſtice, and he is ſignefied to us as a Prieſt of the moſt high God.</p>
               <p>They ſay that God ſeparated theſe two Governments after the going out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> giving the politique to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the care of holy things to <hi>Aaron:</hi> This Objection is ill grounded for two Reaſons; the firſt is becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> were of the ſame Family and Brother-Germanes, ſo theſe two Powers were in a manner in the ſame perſon; and ſecondly, <hi>Moſes</hi> who according to this opinion was in the quality of King to govern the Politique did he not meddle with that of Religion? He who cenſured <hi>Aaron</hi> vigorouſly after his ſinfull compliance to the Golden-Calfe? who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58669:8"/>cauſed the Idol to be broke to Pouder and made it be diſeſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by thoſe who had adored it, who received and gave all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the building of the Tabernacle and for the regulating of the Sacrifices, and who condemned and puniſhed him, who was found carrying wood on the holy day of Reſt? <hi>Moſes</hi> took theſe cares, and theſe Authorities.</p>
               <p>In the proceſs of time the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> who have had the knowledg and zeal of Religion have they not medled with it? <hi>Joaſh, Ezekias, Aza</hi> and <hi>Joſias,</hi> did they not break the Idols to pieces, cauſe the Law of God to be ſearched for, and re-eſtabliſh the true ſervice of the antient Religion appointed by the voice of God himſelf.</p>
               <p n="7">7. But to come to the times of the Goſpel, <hi>Jeſus,</hi> head and &amp; finiſher of our Faith, did not take his birth according to the fleſh in the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> but in that of <hi>Judah,</hi> and in the houſe of <hi>David</hi> where is found the Royal Dignity of the Hebrews; and he who ought to be eternal Prieſt according to the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedeck,</hi> hath willed that his Pontifique grandeur, be in ſome manner ingrafted upon the Royal; they publiſhed his Birth, they took off the ſhame of his Death by the title of King, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe taking the quality of it when he anſwered thoſe who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him, <hi>Art thou King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Yes I am;</hi> It is then true that the care of Prieſts and Kings cannot be judged incompatible; but it behooveth us, to take ſingular notice of this ſplendid Alliance and of the miraculous conduct of God in it.</p>
               <p>We find not that Prieſts have become Kings and preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſought after Empires; but we find that Princes by their Birth or by the Election of Divine Providence have been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Prieſts.</p>
               <p>God hath not permitted that high Prieſts ſhould be made Kings to increaſe their Vanity, but that Princes or Sovereigns ſhould take upon them the Pontifical care and title to enlarge and crown their Piety; Paganiſme it ſelf never ſaw the Roman Prieſts raiſed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58669:8"/>to an Empire, but the Emperours were bound with the Title and Authority of Prieſts, &amp; we may ſee in ancient Medals, they did En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave, <hi>Tib. Nero, Pont. Max. Traj. Imper. Pont. Max. Heliogabalus ſummus ſacerdos;</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. he hath made us Kings and Prieſts.</p>
               <p n="8">8. I do not pretend to maintain that all Kings ought to joyn to their ſoveraign Empire all the actual performances of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of God, but I cannot but believe, that they ought to have a moſt diligent care to maintain it with Purity, or to re-eſtabliſh it after any introduced Corruption.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſhua</hi> was neither of the Family nor of the actual office of Prieſts, nevertheleſs from that very time that the holy Hiſtory repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to us his Employ, which was to conduct the people in War; it gives us alſo to know the commandment which God gave him to ſtudy the divine Law without ceaſing, and to turn neither to the left nor right Hand; he performed conſequently all the actions of a Prince who took care of Religion, he ſaid to the Peoples, <hi>Sanctifie your ſelves;</hi> he ordered all the preparation for the Ark and the Prieſts; in going to <hi>Jordan</hi> he commanded them by order from God himſelf, that they ſhould raiſe up a heap of Stones for a Pious Memorial of Gods Goodneſs, and he Ehxorted the People to to ſerve God with thankfulneſs.</p>
               <p>After that Chriſtianity had taſted the Pleaſure of Quietude for ſome Years, did not <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great order the Biſhops to aſſemble at <hi>Nice,</hi> where he himſelf ſate Preſident in perſon, &amp; the Biſhops of thoſe times made no Scruple of propoſing Ecleſiaſtiques to the Prince, ſince they preſented him with an Account of all their Diſputes; and though he would not judg of them but caſt the Writings into the Fire, yet his great Diſcretion was a prudent Management of his Grandeur, either to Confound or Convert them: Thoſe that ſhall read that which paſſed in the Churches ſome Ages after, will ſee that the Sovereign-Authority of Princes hath regulated the conduct of Synods after they had aſſembled them; the Emperour <hi>Arcadius</hi> ſent Count <hi>Candigian</hi> to Rule in his Name the Synod at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> that of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> had for its
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58669:9"/>Soveraign Preſident the Emperour <hi>Mortian</hi> or the Commiſſaries whom he Deputed, and that of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> held in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Palace was governed by the order of <hi>Conſtantine Le-Barbu</hi> the Emperour.</p>
               <p>The celebrated Author of the Hiſtory of the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> ſpecified all theſe paſſages to draw this concluſion in the ſecond Book, that it was a cuſtom very proper where they governed with Liberty, which was when the world was without a Pope, <hi>il che come e un uſo molto proprio, diove ſi Governa in Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, quale era all hora quando il mondo era ſenza Papa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the Empire of the Weſt was governed by the houſe of <hi>France, Charlemaing</hi> the Emperour preſerved his Power Gloriouſly, which his Succeſſors have loſt by too much yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The Acts of the Council of <hi>Mayence</hi> held in the Year 813 under the Authority of that Emperour, began with theſe Words <hi>to Charles Auguſtus Governor of the true Religion, and Frotector of the Holy Church of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Council held at the ſame Place, gave the ſame Title to <hi>Lewis</hi> the Emperour ſurnamed the <hi>Debonair;</hi> and in the Records of the Synod named <hi>Francisque,</hi> we may read the procedings of <hi>Carloman</hi> under the title of Duke &amp; Prince of the <hi>French,</hi> who ſpoke in this manner; <hi>we have ordained Biſhops in every City, and have Eſtabliſhed over them the Arch-Biſhop Boniface</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All thoſe who have any knowledg in Hiſtory, know that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> (whom they give out and believe at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to be ſo ſoveraignly Soveraign) have written to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours as to their Maſters, and asked Pardons or Favours, &amp; intreated to have Synods in the ſtile of humble Suppliants.</p>
               <p>We read that the Emperour <hi>Charlemaign</hi> took (without contradiction) the liberty of chuſing the Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Books of <hi>Stella, Platin</hi> and of <hi>Sigonius</hi> teſtify that this right was preſerved a long time after.</p>
               <p>When the Empire paſſed into the houſe of <hi>Saxony, Otho</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58669:9"/>Pope <hi>John</hi> the Thirteenth and put <hi>Leo</hi> the Eighth in his Place, and another <hi>Otho</hi> cauſed the Eyes of <hi>John</hi> the Seventeeth to be put out becauſe he reſiſted <hi>Bruno</hi> a Germane named <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Fifth which the Emperour had choſe Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the Wiſe and Prudent ſearch over the Antiquities in the Hebrew and Chriſtan Churches, and they will find that Princes have never made any ſcruple to regulate Religion.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If Authority upholds my thoughts, reaſon, either natural or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique will be advantagious to them; ſince that Monarchs cannot as ſure themſelves of the wellfare of their Countrey, the dignity of their condition, nor the quiet of their minds if they take no care in the government of Religion.</p>
               <p>Let us conſider the condition of Sovereigns without having any reſpect to the practice of Religion; we cannot deny that they are eſtabliſhed in the conduct of two things which appears more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant in the politique ſtate; the firſt is War againſt a forreign ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; the ſecond is Juſtice againſt the wicked men in his own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Theſe two actions which ought to take up all royal Authority, obliged the Hebrewes (when they demanded a King) to ſay, that we alſo may be like all the nations, and that our King may judg us and go out before us and fight our battels <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.8.20.</p>
               <p>But ſince one cannot reject the thoughts of St. <hi>Paul</hi> when he ſaith that righteouſneſs is profitable for all things, one ought to believe that war is an unhappineſs, and that juſtice cannot ſubſiſt without true Piety; from whence it was that the generous and wiſe <hi>Joſhua,</hi> ſeeing himſelf ready to make war againſt the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels heard theſe Words; Streng then thy ſelf and be not diſmaied, the Lord is with thee whither thou goeſt.</p>
               <p>And when he went to do juſtice to <hi>Hacon</hi> he ſaid to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Sanctify your ſelves for to morrow, and ſay to the ſinners, give I pray you glory to the God of <hi>Iſrael; Joſhua</hi> 7.19, 17; from whence I conclude, that the King who will ſucceed well in both his politique Employs, ought neceſſarily to take a ſpecial care to eſtabliſh the true Religion, and to rule his conduct he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58669:10"/>ought to remember that which God ſaid to Joſhua; <hi>Fortify thy ſelf more &amp; more to the end thou mayſt take care to do according to all the law which</hi> Moſes <hi>my ſervant hath commanded thee, and turn neither to the right hand nor to the left that thou mayſt proſper whither ſoever thou goeſt,</hi> Joſh. 1.7.</p>
               <p>He ought to remember the command of God, which orders that the King ſitting upon the throne of his Kingdome ſhould take a Copy of the written Law, and read it every day that he might learn to Fear the Lord: Let not his Heart be lifted up above his brethren, let him not turn from this Law neither to the right nor left hand; Let his dayes be long, and let him reign, him and his Poſterity in the midſt of Gods people.</p>
               <p>I know not how one can maintain, (after this reaſon confirmed by Sacred Authority) that the King doth an unjuſt Action if he takes care of Religion; is it not the perfect Equity of the divine Law, which conducts principally the orders of War and rules of Juſtice? and cannot one eaſily prove that War is a tyrannick uſurper or a ſavage beaſtlineſs, if not bridled by Religion? is it not true that without Piety (which begets the fear of God), the Authority of the Magiſtrate is barbarouſly Executed &amp; unprofitably Eſtabliſhed? for without Religion men would be as imaged Lions, but Juſtice would deſtroy them all if ſhe were ſtrong enough, but where ſhe ſuffers all ſhe is found weak: if then the King is the firſt Captain and the firſt Magiſtrate of his Kingdome, he may name himſelf and ought to appear the principal Biſhop.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The King may find a great advantage in the words of <hi>St. Paul,</hi> who ſpeakes very Chriſtianly, when he ordered that Subjects ſhould be held under the Powers Authorized by God, not only to ſhun the violence of anger, but to acquit themſelves alſo of the duties of conſcience: This Doctrine eſtabliſheth obedience in the Subject more ſtrongly by Religion than by Force. If then the King will preſerve himſelf in a juſt and full Authority, his care muſt be to endeavour to Eſtabliſh true Religion, which tyeth the Subjects more to his will than Force, or Puniſhments, which make the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58669:10"/>People fear the effects of its violence; judg conſequently what is the Concluſion of the intereſted hypocritical Party who leave the Princes but a mean power of making themſelves to be obeyed, in taking away from them the care of Godlineſs which is the ſtrongeſt and moſt ſure power.</p>
               <p>The fear of Puniſhment may hinder the riſeing of rebels, but true Religion will ſtifle the deſign, and not admit a thought of it.</p>
               <p n="11">11. When a Monarch underſtands that a good Conſcience, is the ſtrongeſt and moſt aſſured Principle to hold the Subjects in a ſweet obedience; and when he is perſwaded, that minds which are Led or conducted by true Piety, ſtifle all the motions of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, by the fear of the judgments of God; his own intereſt with the publique peace will engage him to take care to eſtabliſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which hinders them from committing actions of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. The well fare of his State and the quiet of his Perſon ought to make him act ſo judiciouſly as not to permit, that pretence to Religion ſhould imprint in the minds of his People, a falſe Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which inclines them to deſpiſe his Perſon and Ordinances, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of revengeing Gods quarrel, and protecting the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Church.</p>
               <p>The Age in which we live as well as thoſe which have gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, have proved what dreadfull effects falſe &amp; intereſted Piety have produced againſt our Kings; and on the contrarie, the holy Hiſtory, and ſome Chronicles of State, ſhew us how much a good Conſcience and true Religion are reſpectfull to their King, even in the hearts of thoſe Subjects who are harſhly treated by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>David</hi> being unjuſtly perſecuted by his prince <hi>Saul,</hi> might have found an occaſion to take away his life ſecretly in the darkneſs of a Cave, but his good Conſcience obliged him to reſpect an unjuſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, of whom he might have rid himſelf, if he had not feared to offend againſt the juſtice of God; after the miſchance, or rather the decree of the judgment of God, that cauſed <hi>Saul</hi> to periſh, Conſcience alone (produced and governed by a true Religion)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58669:11"/>obliged <hi>David</hi> to weep for it, and to reveng the death of that wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Prince, whom God himſelf had rejected.</p>
               <p>Religion truly Chriſtian counſels ſuch practices of patience and goodneſs, with which he King ought to be ſatisfied, but that Religion, which perſwades co contrary maximes, is dangerous, and the King may render himſelf judg of it, at leaſt he may believe himſelf maſter in his own houſe without being ſubject to thoſe who would limit his power, and who teach the common people to watch for an opportunity of revolting and diſobedience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the 8th being at <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6th of the houſe of <hi>Borgir,</hi> who became an odious, hated, wicked man, was intreated by all the Cardinals (except two) to defend the holy Church againſt the violence of that Pope, who was rather a ſucceſſor of <hi>Judas</hi> then of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and given more to the Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran than to the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>There are no true and natural French men, who will conteſt with the King the power of repreſſing the boldneſs of thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Devoto's,</hi> who teach that Kings Excommunicated by the Pope are no more Kings, and that they are no more any thing to their ſubjects being nothing to the Pope.</p>
               <p>I dare not Speak the reſt it being ſo full of horror; ſee the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of <hi>Sorbonne</hi> againſt <hi>Vernant</hi> and Guimenaeus.</p>
               <p>Can one believe that <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12th had no right to ſuppreſs the wicked doctrine and hector like piety off <hi>Julius</hi> 2d, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſo many wickedneſſes againſt the quiet of this excellent Prince, that he cauſed to be ſtamped upon his coin; I will deſtroy the whore of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Navar John</hi> 2d depoſed by the ſame Pope; ought he in his condition, to deteſt or adore the Religious thoughts of this very Pope told him by a <hi>Spanird</hi> in theſe words: I muſt aid the King of <hi>Spain</hi> and employ my two Swords, both Spiritual and temporal againſt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Navar</hi> who are enemies to all honeſt people.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:58669:11"/>
               <p>Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5th. was reſolved to Excommunicate <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>Navar,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> Prince <hi>Conde,</hi> his Bull ſaid, that he would draw the ſword of Vengeance againſt <hi>Henry,</hi> late King of <hi>Navar,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>Conde,</hi> a Baſtard and Deteſtable Generation; that he did declare them and their Succeſſors to be deprived of all their Lordſhips, Lands, and Dignities: Had not theſe Princes ſome right to reſiſt this violence, and cauſe to be Preached (one to his Subjects, and the other to his Vaſſals) that Religion and Conſcience obliged them not to follow the Paſſions and Uſurpations of this Roman Biſhop?</p>
               <p>Royal Dignity is of a larger extent than vulgar thoughts can apprehend, and beyond the limits which the Ambitious and Covetuous men do preſcribe it, for their own advantage, by an affected or ignorant malice.</p>
               <p>This Royal greatneſs is joyned to the Pontifical, by a kind of neceſſity, from which it cannot be parted, neither by Reaſon nor Conſcience; and though the King doth not execute actually the functions of it, yet he ought to render them ſo really effected, that true Judgment and Power ſhould maintain them, and put them in good order.</p>
               <p>The animated heats againſt my Propoſition, oppoſeth the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of King <hi>Hozias,</hi> when he offered Incenſe upon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of perfumes; but thoſe who conſider his crime, will find that he offended (by neglect, or by Pride) againſt an expreſs order E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by Divine Authority, which ordained that the <hi>Levites</hi> only ſhould ſerve in the Miniſtry, excluding every other Family and Perſon, whether Royal, or not.</p>
               <p>If this Prince had commanded the Sacrifices and Incenſe to be performed as God had ordered him, I do not believe that he had been reproved either by God, or Man.</p>
               <p>My notion proves it ſelf by the words of the high Prieſt, which attributes to the King, only the ſin of contradicting Gods order in theſe words, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.18. It appertaineth not unto thee to burn Incenſe unto the Lord, but to the Prieſts, the Sons of <hi>Aaron</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58669:12"/>that are Conſecrated to burn Incenſe; in the 4. Chap. of <hi>Numb.</hi> you may ſee the Law expreſly.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Uzza</hi> not being of the Family of <hi>Levi,</hi> was ſtricken by God, becauſe he ſtretched forth his hand, to touch, and bear up the Ark, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.9. Theſe examples cannot prove, but that a Chriſtian King may have the care of Religion, and of the Law of God.</p>
               <p>The Head and Finiſher of our Faith, Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of the living God, hath not bound the exerciſes of Religion to ſome particular people &amp; conditions; all thoſe who have Authority do not ſin, if they imploy it in the Service of the all-powerful God; if a Father oweth this juſtice to his Children, a King, certainly, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to it for his Subjects: Do you think that the King doth commit an Injuſtice againſt God, when he cauſeth Juſtice to be Executed among men?</p>
               <p n="12">12. Since all which, I have ſhewed, proveth, that the King may, and ought in Conſcience to have the care of Religion, ſince he may deſire, moſt Lawfully, that there be but one Religion in his Government; I believe that the firſt <hi>Idea</hi> which can open the way to effect it, is to reſolve, that no ſtranger ſhall govern it; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my thoughts, all the <hi>French</hi> of either Religion, wiſh, or ought paſſionately to wiſh for it, both in Reaſon and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for when the King gives, or permits to a Stranger, the Government of Religion in his Kingdome, he keeps to himſelf the leaſt part of his Riches, and puts into the hands of another po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer (which it may be will War againſt him) the Government of thoſe affections, which tye moſt effectually Subjects to Princes.</p>
               <p>What ſhould one ſay, if the King ſhould ſuffer himſelf to be perſwaded to take a <hi>Polonian</hi> to Command all his Army in chief, or a <hi>Spaniard</hi> for his Lord-Chancellour? by what Reaſon can one oblige him to have a Patriarch of <hi>Greece, Alexandria,</hi> or <hi>Italy?</hi> Muſt the King commit that which is moſt conſiderable for his quiet and ſafety, to ſuch an Authority as doth not care for his welfare, or it may be are Enemies to it?</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58669:12"/>
               <p>All <hi>France</hi> ſighs at the remembrance of theſe Devotions, (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther promoted by Devils themſelves, than by Diabolical men) which made <hi>Clement Jacobin, John Chaſtel, Ravillas,</hi> and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally all the League, act by a helliſh zeal: All this myſtery of Iniquity took its birth, progreſs, and execution from a falſe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Conſcience, which the Out-landiſh Beaſt cauſed to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the people, and which had at the bottom nothing but a fatal machin of Intereſt and Ambition.</p>
               <p>I have read in <hi>Avila</hi> an <hi>Italian</hi> Author, that <hi>Jacobin</hi> the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. was a falſe <hi>devote,</hi> and a furious Zealot for the Orders of the Pope.</p>
               <p>We read in <hi>lib.</hi> 95. of the Hiſtory written by <hi>Mouns,</hi> the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of <hi>Thou,</hi> that Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fifth, commended in a full Conſiſtory, this horrible action; with large praiſes, admiring the Vertue of this man, the ſtrength of his Courage, and his ardent Love towards God; <hi>Cum virtutem, hominis, animi robur, &amp; fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventem erga Deum amorem, ſuprà Eliazarem &amp; Juditham multis verbis extollit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Chaſtel</hi> was another <hi>devote,</hi> and the decree of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given againſt his wicked act, is Excommunicated in <hi>Rome,</hi> of whom the wiſe Cardinal of <hi>Oſsat</hi> ſpake in this ſort to the Cardinal <hi>Aldobrandin,</hi> as he himſelf reported, [<hi>If the King had any cauſe to fear to be Murdered, he ſhould rather fear the</hi> Hugonots <hi>whom he had forſaken, and who had cauſe to complain of him;</hi>] but they have attempted nothing like this, neither againſt him, nor againſt the five Kings, his Predeceſſors, whatever Butchery they have made of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ravillac,</hi> another <hi>devoto,</hi> began his day by the Confeſſion, Maſs or Communion, and imploy'd the reſt of it, to follow the Kings Coach to find the occaſion, which he met with (to the great dammage of the Kingdome) after 6 months ſpent in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, and his Indefatigable cares.</p>
               <p>The Zeal of a deſperate man (which he witneſſed in his tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and at the point of his death) ſheweth us, what a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58669:13"/>thing it is for a Stranger to govern the Conſciences, when the Natural King hath nothing but the Political to govern.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Can a State be happily Govern'd when two Monarchs are equally conſidered in it; their Intereſts do undoubtedly divide and part their minds, hearts, and hands; this diviſion produceth Confuſions without Remedy; the wiſeſt men commit the greateſt errors in this Miſt, which permits not the right diſcerning of Juſtice, or Injuſtice between theſe two parties.</p>
               <p>But if one be perſwaded that one of theſe two Monarchs is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, and that one is obliged by Conſcience to take his part, all the people will take his Intereſt, and look upon all that which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth his deſign, as a Horror and a Curſe: If a Stranger, or the Pope, Eſtabliſheth his power in <hi>France,</hi> by the principles of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, his Authority muſt infallibly triumph over that of the King, who is the lawful Prince of it, and this cannot be avoided; for the Superſtitious will fear to be Condemned; and the Perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Intereſted ones, make the weak capacities of others ſerve for their more bold deſigns; and the beſotted Worſhippers will believe to gain as many Crowns in Heaven, as they kill Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</p>
               <p>What Prince can be ſafe (reading and believing the diſcourſe) of the Crowning of the Pope, attributed to <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. and ſaying theſe great words? <hi>I bear the</hi> Mitre, <hi>becauſe of my Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; the Crown, becauſe I am King; Eſtabliſhing my ſelf next under him, who writ upon his Thing, the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</hi> What wonder is there, that ſo many people did riſe againſt <hi>Hen.</hi> 3d. and afterwards againſt the generous and good King <hi>Hen.</hi> 4th? Few perſons could reſiſt thoſe barking Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, who being ingaged in the Popes party, did publiſh through all the Kingdom, <hi>That whoſoever ſhould ſerve the Prince, could never eſcape Damnation;</hi> that Kings loſe their Power in loſing the Friendſhip of the Pope; and being in that condition, they merit neither Reſpect nor Love.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58669:13"/>
               <p>Judg Sir, if the King hath not a juſt Intereſt, and a lawful Right to cauſe his Nation to love a Religion which hath but one God, one Heaven, and one Monarch upon Earth.</p>
               <p n="14">14. If the King deſigns this Unity, of which you tell me, the true fear of God ought to poſſeſs his Soul; he ought to think that he is a Soveraign over his People; but yet that he is neither Maſter of, nor Companion with God, and then he will account it his greateſt glory to appear a faithful Servant in the houſe of the Almighty; this title was given to <hi>Moſes</hi> when he governed the <hi>Hebrews; David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> were honoured with that quality. Certainly to ſerve God, is, truly to Reign; his Majeſty ought to take this Reſolution, not to conſider the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, Flatteries, the Threatnings, Opinions, or the Wills of Men, but only the Truth of God, which conducts to true Juſtice.</p>
               <p>Princes are obliged to know that God alone is the Monarch of Conſciences, and his Law only ought to inſtruct, and his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to engage.</p>
               <p>When they ſay that the King permits Liberty of Conſciences, they underſtand the liberty of exerciſing it, or the liberty of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing what one is, ſince the freedome of thoughts anſwers but to God only.</p>
               <p>It is certain then that the King, deſiring to draw his Subjects into one Religion, cannot ſucceed more nobly, nor more uſefully, then in eſtabliſhing the way and orders of God, the common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all; no body can exclaim againſt his Powers, cenſure his Word, nor condemn his Ordinances.</p>
               <p>Excellent Kings are marked with the quality of Princes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods own heart, becauſe they have care to order to be done, not what mens hearts deſire, but what God loves.</p>
               <p>Sovereigns, who render themſelves ſubject to the Wills of men, whither to their own Subjects, or Strangers, divide Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and give birth to War; but if they appear faithful Servants to God, and requite no more from the people, but what God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58669:14"/>himſelf requireth, then the people give to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and to God, that juſtice and obedience which is due to them by one and the ſame act; becauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> deſires all, and only that which GodS Wills.</p>
               <p n="15">15. When the vulgar ſpeak of the uniting of the two Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in <hi>France,</hi> they ſpeak of a thing impoſſible; becauſe they conſiſt of Propoſitions, which are named Contradictories, of which the firſt are neceſſarily falſe, if the Oppoſites are true, in this condition they can never be united, as may be ſeen by theſe Examples; one maintaining that the body of Chriſt in his very Fleſh, Blood, and Bones, is really preſent in the Sacrament; the other ſaying, that there is no reality of fleſh, though there be a real preſence and ſpiritual grace: Can theſe two Notions unite, and be conjoyned? one ſaith, the ſouls ſeparated from the bodies, being in a ſtate of grace, burn in a fire under-ground, to ſatisfie for their ſins; the other holds, that ſouls juſtified by grace, have no obſtacle which can hinder them from poſſeſſing or injoying glory.</p>
               <p>One affirmeth, that the Pope is Monarch of all Kings and Biſhops, with the ſame power which Chriſt had when he was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth; the other is perſwaded that this Biſhop hath not this power, and that he can neither maintain it without error, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe it without Tyranny; theſe propoſitions can never agree, and if one would ſpeak rightly of the deſign of his Majeſty, we muſt interpret it a unity of good Society, which may be effected; but not a unity of Conformity, which can never be.</p>
               <p n="16">16. I believe, that (according to the Kings will) thoſe of both Religions, may agree in the ſame thoughts, and make but one Religion both good and pious.</p>
               <p>In the fourth Age, all Chriſtendom was divided upon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of the Divinity of Chriſt; theſe two Propoſitions, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt is God in ſubſtance, and Chriſt is not God in ſubſtance, but by reſemblance, are diſcourſes and notions never to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled. In a word, after many unjuſt Fends of the one and other Party, all did agree after the Truth was juſtly known, and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſought after.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:58669:14"/>
               <p>We might experiment the ſame unity, if minds would ceaſe to be prae-poſſeſs'd by Intereſt or Cuſtome; Let us ſearch with ſincerity the will of God, and the reality of his thoughts, and then we ſhall eaſily be of one mind, piouſly following that which God bids us.</p>
               <p n="17">17. This Union of Minds in the ſame apprehenſions of things, cannot be done with fatisfaction, if, (as ſome pragmatically ſay) the King ſhould uſe his abſolute Authority without ſuffering any diſputes about it.</p>
               <p>One [I Will,] is not enough to perſwade the profound Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Soul: One [I Will not] cannot root out the firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; all the effects that theſe commands can produce, is terrour or diſſembling; one may ſtudy to hide one ſelf for fear of anger, for the reſpect one ought to have for his Majeſty; but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one will keep thoſe thoughts which he thinks neceſſary for his Salvation; What pleaſure can the King have to ſee his Realm full of Diſſemblers, who fear his Anger; or of miſerable ones, if he ſhould uſe Violence?</p>
               <p n="18">18. They rank that which you told me, of the Embaſſage to <hi>Rome</hi> to obtain a permiſſion for a Conference about Religion; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the ill news we hear, His Majeſty hath too much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the practices of the Romiſh Court, to expect that the Pope ſhould give him liberty to argue againſt him, and his Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Power: Dare the Signiorle of <hi>Venice,</hi> ask the King of <hi>Spain</hi> the power to debate, whither the Dutchie of <hi>Milan,</hi> and the Kingdome of <hi>Naples</hi> belong to him by a Ligitimate Right?</p>
               <p>Can one believe that Romane Polity hath ever been ſo civil to praiſe Catholick Majeſty, to ordain a conference upon the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of <hi>Sicily;</hi> and that it hath ever asked the liberty to publiſh the Bull <hi>(in canâ Domini)</hi> in the Lords Supper, by which that King is Excommunicated?</p>
               <p>The King is not under Age, let him govern his Subjects in the fear of God, even from the bottom of our Souls we all deſire it; and thoſe who would not have it ſo, are neither, Rational nor
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58669:15"/>French-men; Can we be in a better hand than that of a King, who ſpeaks our own Language, whom Nature engageth to cheriſh his Country, whoſe Inclinations are agreeable to our Climate, which is his, and whoſe Intereſts are neceſſarily tyed to ours?</p>
               <p>Let the King freely take his own; let no body diſpute it in his Kingdome; let no Stranger rule over us: It is one of the moſt horrible puniſhments which God hath brought upon his people; of which the <hi>Hebrews</hi> complain moſt bitterly, and which may be compared to the crime, of which the Lord himſelf complains in <hi>Jerem.</hi> 2.25. <hi>But thou ſayeſt there is no hope, no, for I have lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Strangers, and after them will I go;</hi> and in Jerem. 5. <hi>You ſhall ſerve Strangers;</hi> in Lament. 2. <hi>Our Heritage hath been overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Strangers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not the King a Chriſtian, and, <hi>The moſt Chriſtian King?</hi> is he not a Sacred perſon? is he not the Lords Anoynted? ought he to ask the Pope leave to ſearch the true Law of God, and to offer it naked to his people?</p>
               <p>Let the King ſpeak as the generous <hi>Henry le Grand</hi> for his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſdome of <hi>Salus,</hi> he anſwered to all the cunning devices of Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the 8th. and the addreſſes of Cardinal <hi>Aldobran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din,</hi> and the Artifices of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> with theſe words, <hi>[I will have my Own.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the Kings right to propoſe the Law of God, as tis his duty to ſearch and meditate it; hath not he, as well as the Prince of <hi>Rome,</hi> both <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, the Holy Hiſtory, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Apoſtles, and the Confeſſion of Faith, of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice?</hi> hath he not as much Ingenuity, and as Penetrating a Wit as the Pope, to diſcern Good from Evil, Truth from Falſhood, and Sincerity from Intereſt? hath he not more Zeal, or more Natural Inclination for the good of his Subjects, than a Stranger, who appears to all reaſonable men, to make no Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of any thing, if he can but raiſe never ſo little, his glory and advantage by it.</p>
               <p>Will he take meaſure from the Pope, to oblige the <hi>French</hi> to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58669:15"/>give their Souls to God, rendring their Reſpects to their King? can any one believe that <hi>France</hi> hath no body in it who is enlivened with a Zeal by a ſincere and unſpotted Soul, and by an inlightened Piety? Can his Majeſty expect Know ledge and Conſcience from <hi>Italy,</hi> to make us Famous and Conduct us.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Believe Sr. that if the King hath deſigned that, of which we diſcourſe, he hath too much Grandeur and Light in his Mind, to commit it to the Pope or acquaint him with it.</p>
               <p n="19">19. If the Pope ſhould admit of this Conference, he would never ſuffer that any thing ſhould be concluded on to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage; no one hates his own Fleſh. The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> was a mighty Aſſembly, whither the <hi>French</hi> ſent Eminent Men, but <hi>Rome</hi> never permitted that any one ſhould propoſe any thing whereby his Glory or his Intereſt ſhould be Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.</p>
               <p>This Conference which you ſpeak of, will give ſomething or nothing to that Religion which is not approved of by <hi>Rome;</hi> if it gives any thing it will certainly be diſowned by the Pope, and perhaps Excommunicated; If it denies every thing to the Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> it will be very unuſeful to the Kings deſign, who will not without doubt ruine his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by violence, but make a peaceable and voluntary agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>'Tis then moſt certain, that if an Aſſembly depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Pope, and if thoſe who compoſe that Aſſembly are pre-admoniſhed or tied to manage the intereſt of the Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Court, ſuſpition or hatred will accompany its Birth, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſs its Progreſs, and bitterneſs its End.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Rather than be hindred by the delayes of <hi>Rome</hi> and choice of a Deputy for this Conference, all <hi>France</hi> ſhould u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite &amp; with an unanimous Conſent, beſeech the King, that he would inform himſelf of the differences of the two Religions,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58669:16"/>&amp; pitch upon a certain Form, ſince Heaven hath made him to be looked upon by all the World, as a Prince who hath a moſt juſt Genius, a moſt ſolid Judgment, and Parts not Confuſed in any thing he undertakes; one cannot think that his Majeſty can charge his Memory or weary his Eyes with the Myſteries and Wranglings of Controverſies; but after ſome Love to, and ſome Practice of the Sacred Books, where the Law of God is found ſo much recommended to Princes by holy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, his Majeſty may diſtinguiſh exactly enough what Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is moſt proper to be Allowed, and to tie the Soul to God without Violence, Confuſion and Hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>Hath not the King (who is very judicious) diſcerned that the form of Adminiſtring juſtice, would defer the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and that introduced Corruption followed by Cuſtome had need to be Corrected; hath not theſe Thoughts made his Majeſty be Approved &amp; Bleſſed by all the reaſonable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intereſted People, when he made his Commands to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed and kept, which among the common ſort are Named <hi>Le code Louis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King can very well diſtinguiſh, whether the Counſel and Advice which they give him, does bear the Character of Freedom, the Principle of good Meaning, and be uſeful for his Deſigne: When he pleaſes to bow himſelf a little from his Majeſtique Grandeur, to converſe; the eaſily knows whether he be a man that expreſſeth himſelf by a heap of unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and windy Words, or whether he uſeth Neat, Clear and apt Expreſſions; he need not ſtudy much to underſtand the Air of an affected Woman, who defires to appear fine by fading and ridiculous ornaments; by the ſame Genius his Majeſty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble underſtands the comlineſs of a well-made Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who appears in her own Colours without Paint or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe with the Characters of a generous Vertue.</p>
               <p>This judicious Prince, (who conſidereth all that he ſeeth, who weighs every thing that he apprehends, and apprehends
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58669:16"/>every thing that comes before him) can with eaſe exactly judg of the Intereſt, Fraud, Amuſements, affected Pomps, Artifices, Politique Intereſts, induſtrious Covetouſneſs, and the h, pocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Characters of Religion.</p>
               <p n="21">21. If the King would leſſen his Trouble, he may Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any one to give him an Account what was demanded in the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> to reform the Abuſes introduced in Religion; and particularly, his Majeſty may pleaſe to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice what the French Embaſſadors Treated of in former Complaints of Proteſtations or Demands; of which you may ſee a ſmall Abridgment. drawn from the Hiſtory of the Council, which learns us the Negotiations of <hi>Amiot, Pibrac Ferrier, Lanſac</hi> and of the Cardinal of <hi>Lorain</hi> who appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for <hi>France.</hi> At diverſe Times and at divers Concluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions of this Synod, they Demanded,</p>
               <p>That the Sacrament ſhould be Celebrated with the Cup, according to the Order of Jeſus Chriſt and the Ancient Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omes of the Church.</p>
               <p>That their might be Aboliſhed many Abuſes Introduced by Images, Reliques, Pilgrimages and other ſuch-like Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>That they would Reform the Abuſes committed by the Mendicant Fryers.</p>
               <p>That they would Permit Eccleſiaſtiques to Marry.</p>
               <p>That they would receive no Paſtors without having a Flock, and without being able to Preach the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>That Divine Service be read in a Tongue underſtood by all.</p>
               <p>That they would reduce the Monks to their firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which obligeth them to work with their Hands, and not to meddle with Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, unleſs they be ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employed by the Biſhops.</p>
               <p>That Paſtors ſhould be Reſident at their Churches.</p>
               <p>That Ecleſiaſtical Donations be employed and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58669:17"/>according to the juſt intention of thoſe who gave them, for the Poor, for Schools, and for the preachers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.</p>
               <p>That they ſhould not give to Tradition the ſame Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as to the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>That before the Adminiſtration of Sacraments, they ſhould expoſe with Clearneſs, their Eſtabliſhment, their Uſe and their Force, in a vulgar Language underſtood by the moſt Ignorant.</p>
               <p>Other Embaſſadors demanded many other things for their Princes and Nations, as the Aboliſhing of firſt Fruits, the reducing the Papal Authority to that which <hi>St. Peter</hi> ſeemed to have taken over the other Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Queen <hi>Katharine</hi> of <hi>Medices,</hi> particularly demanded the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition of the Feaſt of the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, which appeared to be inſtituted rather for Pomp than Piety. Read the ſeventh Book of the Hiſtory of the Council, &amp; there you will ſee all theſe Requeſts, which teſtify that the King of <hi>France</hi> &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes, deſire to Eſtabliſh one only Religion in their Nations, ſuppreſſing the Abuſes of that which was in uſe; of which Abuſes they have taken a pious and juſt Account, that they might ſeparate the good from the Evil.</p>
               <p n="22">22 None can believe that it doth not belong to Kings to judg of Religion, ſince the Embaſſadours (of whom I have already ſpoken) had their Inſtructions from the Soveraigns to whom they were Servants; they propoſed the Thoughts and Deſigns of their Princes; who were ſo far from conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Orders of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they Deliberated, Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and Propounded againſt them: Reaſon and judicious Piety makes Kings ſee the multitudes of Abuſes.</p>
               <p n="23">23. What rational Minds can ignore that our true judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may very eaſily diſcern the Thoughts of a thing, of which we have no practical Experience ſince we know ſome general Principles of it.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58669:17"/>
               <p>I do not profeſs Phyſick, yet I know very well, that exceſs of Wine is dangerous for one in a Fever: Although I am no Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, yet I know, that a bad Husband-man, who never Sows, ſhall never Reap, and that he who breaks the Stalk, when the Ear is formed, doth very ill diſpoſe of his Crop.</p>
               <p>I never was a Servant, yet I know, that he who will do that which pleaſeth himſelf only, (being a Servant) does not his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and runs the danger of being Chaſtiſed or turned away.</p>
               <p>And by the ſame Conſequence, thoſe which have not School-Divinity, have that of Reaſon to diſcern that which hath the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance of being the Principles of good Morality and Piety; they know that Divine Will ought to Govern and Rule theſe Vertues, and then they may believe and conclude that all practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces eſtabliſhed by Humour, or by the Intereſt of Men are Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous, Incertain, Indifferent, or Criminal: And that Prince who bears a good Mind, as well as a good Sword, may as well judg of Religion, as of War; St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf tells us, that the Spiritual man diſcerns all things.</p>
               <p>But without going to ſpiritual exactneſs, I have ſeen Peaſants brought up in the labour of the fields (who being born with good Wit) deſpiſe many Groteſque Devotions, and could diſtinguiſh with a ſolid judgment.</p>
               <p>There is much reaſon to believe, that if his Majeſty would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy his excellent Wit about the two Religions exerciſed in his Kingdom, he would diſcern with an exact clearneſs, the Good from the Evil, the Neceſſary from the Superfluous, Divine from Humane, the True from the Dubious, the Hypocritical from the Sincere, the Dangerous from the Uſeful, the Material from the Spiritual, and the Rational from the Brutal.</p>
               <p>A regular mind eaſily ſeeth that which raiſeth him to Heaven, or that which amuſeth him upon the Earth.</p>
               <p n="24">24. It is certain that his Majeſty may diſcern (without any great difficulty) the form of that Religion, which falls under the knowledg of a good natural judgment; but to ſatisfie himſelf
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58669:18"/>more fully, he may command experienced men, (who are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of greater, labours) to repreſent to him chat which is Old and New, Chriſtian and Roman, Apoſtolical and Pontifical, to the end his Majeſty may be able to diſcern what is eſtabliſhed by the Antiquity of the Apoſtles, and all that which is added by a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Antiquity.</p>
               <p>This Repreſentation cannot be done, but by minds very labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and knowing in both Religions, and whoſe Souls are ſincere and generous.</p>
               <p>They ought alſo to conſider the reſpect they owe to their Prince, and repay his kindneſs with a ſolid ſincerity; by this means one ſhall find that nothing is more ancient than that which is moſt true; and that which doth appear moſt true, will be beſt maintained and defended.</p>
               <p n="25">25. I conſider in the Oeconomy of this Peace, both Royal and Heavenly, that the difficulty muſt be but mean upon the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions diſputed in the Schools by Divines on either ſide, as the myſteries of Juſtification, the grace of Praedeſtination; this Controverſie may raiſe divers Opinions, and yet leave men Friends.</p>
               <p>But the worſt Obſtacle is of Practices, Cuſtoms, and outward Devotions which appear of great moment to the Vulgar, when as they are looked upon but as low things, and indeed but tricks, by Wiſe men.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Roman-Catholick</hi> doth not believe that there can be either Piety or Chriſtianity, where he finds not Images, Ornaments, Ceremonies, Proceſſions, and Pompous Appearances; He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts nothing worthy enough for his Adoration, nor real for his Salvation if one does not perſwade him that Chriſt in the fleſh is kept in a box in the Church; He is much a ſlave to Cuſtom, and believes that the Sacraments and Service adminiſtred privately, and in an unknown Language, where they hear the voice only, without underſtanding the words, begets more Reverence; His mind is ſo ill-diſpos'd by this Cuſtom, that he imagines that all
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58669:18"/>will be in a diſorder, if the King ſhould declare himſelf, next un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God as well Protector of Religion, as of Juſtice; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the loud and continual bawlings of the Emiſſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> He imagins that God will not remain in <hi>France,</hi> if the Pope ſhould not be Mediator between Chriſt and the King, to keep them Friends, without thinking that St. <hi>Peter</hi> (who writ plainly) ſaith, that he that honoureth the King, ſheweth his fear to God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he declareth the near Relation between God and the King, for he writes, <hi>Fear God, and Honour the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such is the diſpoſition of the <hi>Roman-Catholick;</hi> from whence follow ſuch Practices, Devotions, and Cuſtoms which cannot be taken from it without its deſtruction; and one feels as much pain, when one plucks away an unprofitable and idle excreſcence from the fleſh, as in cutting off a Member which is very ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the body.</p>
               <p>The Proteſtant hath a Soul inclined quite another way; He ſeeks God with a Worſhip of Spirit and Truth; He believes not his Faith divinely Eſtabliſhed, but by the Word of God; nor the equity of his Conſcience well regulated, but only by the Law of God; He ſeeks not the fleſh of Jeſus Chriſt upon the Earth, but his Spirit and his Grace; He Worſhips him as he is in Heaven, not by the Image of his body, but in reſpect of his Divinity; he can eaſily paſs by Images and Statues, looking upon them as falſe Repreſentations, and very unprofitable to ſolid P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: If he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteems the Right of the Church, and the Decency of it in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal practice of Religion he deſpiſes the multitude of Proud Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and the glittering of ſo many affected Ornaments; He believes not that the Popes Authority is neceſſary for the <hi>French</hi> Church; He ſaith confidently that the Gallique Church may ſtand without the Roman, and that ſhe can never render her ſelf more juſt and happy, than by baniſhing ſtrange Power: He looks upon the King as the Head of Juſtice, which is principally eſtabliſhed by the Divine Laws, that Sovereigns, who are accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods own heart, ought to know and cauſe to be obſerved
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58669:19"/>the Law of God, without turning either to the right, or to the left hand; with this diſpoſition of mind, ſo different between the Roman-Catholiques and French Proteſtants (if divers Opinions remained in the mind only without breaking forth) they would not produce dreadful Enmities, and thoſe Obſtacles which are ſo hard to be overcome; but when one endeavours to draw a Roman-Catholick from his painted Devotions, and oblige a Proteſtant to conform to them, they ſuffer frightful Vexations if they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, and can hardly take any Reſolutions, except they are brought to them by Reaſonings and Perſwaſions.</p>
               <p n="26">26. I have known the thoughts of many rational minds, even of the Roman-Catholiques, who believe that the King would do an act of Wiſe Bounty, if he would permit (without any reſerve) the ſatisfaction of Conſciences, without ſhewing any averſion, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Proteſtants or Papiſts, provided that all would dwell in a mutual Peace, without malediction or quarelling.</p>
               <p>This State of Ceſſation would be a principle of Peace, and all the World would be contented, if his Majeſty would not permit, that any one of his Subjects ſhould be debarred from bearing Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Honours, that thoſe of either Religion may live without trouble and diſquiet in the Service due to his Majeſty. By this Liberty we ſhould all have a Peaceable Converſation and a Charming Commerce; the heats of diſputes animated by Hatreds, would ceaſe, they would become Conferences of Friendſhip, by which every one might be Inſtructed; Averſion (which diſorders the blood) ſhould have no more force againſt the calme lights of our minds, and all would be ſo agreeably diſpoſed to Truth, that, in a word, all who are Great, Rational, and Spiritual in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, would give their hearts and minds to the moſt juſt verity.</p>
               <p>One may obſerve in the Debates of Religion, that which falls out in all other quarrels;</p>
               <p>One never yields to declared Enemies, till after they have tryed the misfortune of Armes, and then the Submiſſion increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the rage of the Over-come, and begets ſuch grudges as are
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58669:19"/>the Fathers or Children of deſperate Actions; but in a Ceſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Fight, they ſpeak together, they hear one another, they joyn their Intereſts, and every one hath time to do Juſtice to himſelf and others.</p>
               <p>If we could have in <hi>France</hi> ſo ſweet a way to perfect Peace, we ſhould ſee a miraculous effect, and ſooner than one could believe, of this deſired Unity; becauſe every one being diſ-engaged from the Authority of Strangers, (without fearing to be puniſhed by the Kings Orders) would bind himſelf willingly to his Natural Prince, who is moſt Chriſtian; rather than to tye himſelf to the Roman Monarch, who appears very jealous and hard to be ſerved; and ſo not parting their Hearts, they would Unite their Souls.</p>
               <p>If a French-man were in neceſſity of having a Diſpenſation for Marriage, would he not be content rather to obtain it of the King, than to buy it of <hi>Rome?</hi> eſpecially when in theſe days, they coſt four times more than ordinary, to make war againſt <hi>Candia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I believe not but that Paſtors Ordained by the Kings Authority, and Canonically received by the Churches, would be as ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory, and as fully Authorized as by the Power of <hi>Rome;</hi> and when we ſhall have well thought upon the eſtabliſhment of this ſweet Agreement, the Fruits which it will produce, will be found to be the very things which the King deſires for his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p n="28">28. This matter of Religion having been diſcourſed, where there were many of both Religions, one approved the thoughts of a perſon, who maintained that the Roman-Catholiques, whoſe minds are not cruelly inclined, are more eaſily bent to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Piety, than the Reformed to the Romiſh Religion.</p>
               <p>The <hi>1ſt. Reaſon</hi> is, that it is more eaſy to ceaſe believing that which is uncertain, than to begin to believe that which appears to be falſe; for example, I give you the Creed of the reality of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, of the only and Supreme authority of the Pope, of Purgatory and of the glory of the Saints departed whom they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58669:20"/>pray to; The reality of Chriſts being carnally in the bread, is ſo uncertain, that it depends upon the well-making of the bread, the right Ordination of the Prieſt; upon the true Pronuciation of the Words &amp; upon the fixed attention of the Prieſt, all theſe neceſſary conditions are only Suppoſed or believed by a Charitable Faith.</p>
               <p>The Supream Authority of the Pope depends upon his lawful Election, which is often ſo obſcure, and appears ſo clearly defective or ſo openly Criminal, that many Decades of years have paſſed, in which one knew not which Pope to obey if there were two cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and where there is but one, Simony is ſo ordinary that all Popes are Suſpected of it.</p>
               <p>Purgatory is propoſed as a place in the hollow of the earth; holy Authority ſpeaks not a word of it, the Ancients Creed ſpeak no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, the Greek Church deſpiſeth it, eyes cannot ſee it, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot underſtand it, the perfect grace of Chriſt doth not fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour it The viſion of Souls who come again cloathed in White or Red, is much Suſpected for a cheat and convicted of extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; this Myſtery hath nothing more certain than the fear it gives the people and the good it brings to the Prieſts.</p>
               <p>The glory of the ſouls departed to whom they pray, cannot be known but by a popular opinion, which hath but little diſcerning; or by particular perſwaſions which may ſeduce by freindſhip; or by Canonization of the Pope which may be deceived by a falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</p>
               <p>The mind of a Roman-Catholique finding in its ſelf theſe proofs to be ſo uncertain, as well in the Eſſentials as Circumſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials, will have much leſs a do to deny his full conſent, than a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant to give his; becauſe, Reaſon and Faith will fly uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and cannot ſeek for them nor love them: the ſecond Reaſon is, that Roman-Catholiques do believe all that which the Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant do poſitively avow, in reſpect of God, of Jeſus Chriſt, of the bleſſed Virgin, of the life and death eternal, and generally of all myſteries, univerſally received in all Churches where Chriſt is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58669:20"/>worſhipped as God, and known as a Redeemer; In this common belief, it is more eaſie for rational minds tolimit themſelves to this Faith ſo ancient and general, than to encreaſe it by Articles of humane faith, which hath not the principles nor juſt Characters of divine Authority, The third Reaſon is, that the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick may have the ſame comfort of Spirit by the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on having laid aſide the myſteries which are added to the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Faith, that which the Proteſtants may not do when they go to the Roman Communion.</p>
               <p>A Chriſtian ſoul may comfort it ſelf, without the reality of Fleſh if it unites it ſelf Spiritually to Jeſus Chriſt, by having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to him, knowledg of him, and a ſincere Love for him.</p>
               <p>One is more ſatisfied to believe the grace of God capable to carry our ſouls to Heaven, than to leave them at the bottom of a lake of fire;</p>
               <p>The heart is more content to Eſtabliſh its faith, obedience and its good workes upon the Law and words of the Goſpel, then upon the Politiques of the Decretals and upon the Engin, du droit <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prayers have much more juſtice and confiance when they are addreſſed to God, who ſees, underſtands, and fathoms all things, than if they are carried at randome by the Imagination, to get the favour of a Saint whoſe ſtate is unknown to us.</p>
               <p>Theſe three Reaſons, which I ſet down (amongſt many of the ſame force) prove, that the Roman-Catholiques not being corrupted by the advantage of the World, nor upheld by the power of a Soveraign, or animated by violent paſſions, are eaſily carried to the Approbation of that Faith &amp; Piety with which the Proteſtants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves; But the Proteſtant cannot without violence or without intereſt ſubmit to all the particulars of the Roman Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they make the Spiritual adoration, carnall; the Spirit of God, the material Body of Chriſt; Faith in God, Fear; Certainty, Dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; Divinity, humanity, Pure and Efficacious grace a defective and weak merit.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:58669:21"/>
               <p n="29">29. Let us not trouble our ſelves to diſpute, to which way pious Reaſon would turn, if it were at full liberty; whatſoever inſpiration one might pretend to have to preſage, it is the event that muſt make the Prophecy known.</p>
               <p>But to ſee ſome effects in favour of this deſired Unity; The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire liberty of the two Religions will make the only overture to this Royal deſign; and then conſidering no body but the King, next to the Majeſty of God, they will loſe the fears which the thunder of the Vatican gives them, and of which a wife man hath ſaid, <hi>Chi non ha Paura, non ſente il malo;</hi> he who hath no fear can feel no harm.</p>
               <p>No Party ſhould take an advantage of another, and I believe that if we ſerved God well and honoured the King, we ſhould all agree, with ſo much ſweetneſs, that one might ſee faith truly univerſal, juſtly Apoſtolical, and truly Chriſtian, ſhine out clearely.</p>
               <p n="30">30. If to produce unity wee muſt have the ſame thoughts, let us all reſpect &amp; follow (without wrangling) the good will of our Soveraign; let us not be obſtinate in our private faith, but let us be fixed in that which hath appeared at all times Catholique, and which we have equally reſpect for and confiance in.</p>
               <p>All of us have the Confeſſion of Faith which is called the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Symbol, we have almoſt in the ſame words as they recite them in the Maſs, the Confeſſion of Faith of the Council of Nice: ſuch a collection of Faith ſigned by 318 Biſhops was a concluſion of that worthy Aſſembly, to whom Rome ſent two Deputies; the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of faith were received by the Church which was not <hi>Arian,</hi> and ſince none of bur Churches are ſo, let us be ſatisfied with that Confeſſion truly Catholique, and let us hold to it.</p>
               <p>Let us Reaſon together with freindſhip: The Confeſſion of the Symbol of Nice, touched without doubt all the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith which the truly faithfull believe or ought to believe to ſatisfy their conſciences; ſo worthy an Aſſembly was the firſt that Chriſtianity ſaw in its quiet after the dreadfull Perſecutions:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58669:21"/>It was under the Authority of Conſtantine the great, who was converted from Idolatry to the Faith, it was as the Reſurrection of the Goſpel, which untill then was preached in hidden places, in Caves and dark holes of the earth.</p>
               <p>By the happy Miracle of a new Life, Jeſus Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by his Divine Power, the light of Faith and the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of tranquillity; it was neceſſary in ſo conſiderable a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to inform Chriſtians very well what they were obliged to believe always in all parts of the World, and in all Nations where Religion could be found. It was abſolutely neceſſary alſo to inform by a publique Act the Soul of the newly Converted Emperour of all the Myſteries which make Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion Divine and True; and the Emperor ought to Regulate his Faith by that general approved Confeſſion, ſigned by all the good Biſhops. In ſhort this Confeſſion of Faith ſo Authentique and ſo wiſely Eſtabliſhed, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by all Chriſtianity as an abridgment of the Goſpel, with this aſſurance, that thoſe who believe theſe Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, would have that true and entire Faith which Chriſt requires in his Faithfulones.</p>
               <p>All theſe Circumſtances witneſs, that the Articles propoſed ſince that time were not believed then, ſince they could not forget to Record them; and that this Council principally Aſſembled againſt the impious ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Arius,</hi> treated of all the Myſteries of Religion, and by a common Agreement made a general Declaration of them; that they put into it all that is neceſſary to Salvation; not only to correct preſent Errors, but to hinder new ones; and if the blind obedience which Worſhipped the Decrees of the Church, and the Patriarch of <hi>Rome,</hi> had been a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference neceſſary to Salvation, the Roman Deputies would not have ſail'd to preſent it. The Emperour nor the Fathers of the Council would not have neglected to put in that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle which goeth at preſent for the moſt Fundamental Ground
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58669:22"/>of Faith, and inſtead of theſe Words <hi>One Holy and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Church</hi> we ſhould read theſe, the Roman Church only.</p>
               <p>I wonder that if the <hi>Greeks</hi> complain of that which the <hi>Latines</hi> have added to the Articles of the Proceſſion of the holy Spirit <hi>Filioque,</hi> we ſhould not complain of them that they have added. And the Roman Church.</p>
               <p>After having confirmed this Truth, that the Confeſſion of Faith publiſhed by the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> being received by all Chriſtians eſtabliſheth them in a moſt Holy and Pious Unity, let us agree according to the will of the King in the <hi>French</hi> Church, in that manner which the firſt and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Council of Chriſtians, regulated our common Faith; ſince in the third Age it regulated the Faith of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great and all Chriſtianity: we may joine to theſe, thoſe who condemned the Hereſy of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and <hi>Eutichus;</hi> in ſhort we are united if true Antiquity Governs us.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Let us conſider the difference of the firſt Council held at <hi>Nice,</hi> which cements us all, with the laſt held at <hi>Trent</hi> which divides us; I am not willing to utter the leaſt unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming Word, but I muſt ſay, (keeping the Truth which I love) that there is a great difference between him whom the Spirit of the holy Scriptures Governs, and him that takes his from the Valiſes or Clok-bag of <hi>Rome:</hi> In the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> we have nothing which is not propoſed in Holy Writ, by the Miniſtry of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; In that of <hi>Trent,</hi> we ſee all is Propoſed, Reſolved, and Ordained accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the preſcribed Order of the Romane Legates, and according to the Popes intereſt. The firſt which bindes us with the Truth of God, unties us with Pleaſure; the other which makes all ſubmit to the Vanities of the Pope, divides us even to Fury.</p>
               <p>But to make the Purity of that Faith appear the better, which can give us that Admirable Peace, I will employ this Page, to ſet down Word for Word, the Confeſſion of Faith
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58669:22"/>Writ at the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> ſo as it is ſang in the Romane Maſs from whence I took it with exact Faithfulneſs.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Creed.</head>
                     <p>I <hi>Believe in One God, the Father Almighty, Maker of Heaven and Earth, and of all things Viſible and Inviſible; and in One Lord Jeſus Chriſt the only begotten Son of God, begotten of his Father before all Worlds; God of God, Light of Light, very God of very God, begotten not made, being of one Subſtance with the Father, by whom all things were made: Who for us Men and for our Salvation, came down from Heaven, and was Incarnate by the Holy Ghoſt of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and was made Man, and was Crucified alſo for us under</hi> Pontius Pilate: <hi>He ſuffered, and was Buried, and the third Day he Roſe again according to the Scriptures, and Aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth on the Right Hand of the Father: And he ſhall come again with Glory to Judg both the Quick and the Dead, whoſe Kingdom ſhall have no End. And I believe in the Holy Ghoſt, the Lord and giver of Life, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth from the Father and the Son, who with the Father and the Son together is Worſhipped and Glorified, who ſpake by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. And I Believe one Catholick and Apoſtolick Church; I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg one Baptiſme for the Remiſſion of Sins, and I look for the Reſurrection of the Dead and the Life of the World to come,</hi> Amen.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>We are Piouſly and Chriſtianly United by this Creed, and if any thing be omitted in it, it is ſo clear in the Holy Scriptures, that one has no need of a Council to perſwade or declare it. But to follow the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> I muſt add to the Confeſſion of Faith which I have Written, theſe new Articles.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>I Beleive the Patriarch of</hi> Rome <hi>to be Soveraign Monarch and independent of all Chriſtian People above all Lawes, incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be judged either by a Council or any other Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>I Beleive the true Body of Chriſt made ſo by the Prieſt is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58669:23"/>Eaten, Broken, and ſenſibly bruiſed by the Teeth of the Faithful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>I Believe a Purgatory under the Earth, to Torment the Souls deſtined to Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>I Beleive the Indulgences of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>to draw Souls out of that Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>I Believe the Efficacious Abſolution of the Preiſts when one has confeſt all the Sins to them which they have Committed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>I Believe the Canonizing of Saints ordered by the Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>I Believe Images, Reliques Proceſſions, the</hi> Agnus Dei, <hi>the Medals, the Service in an unknown Tongue, the Roſaries, the Girdle of St.</hi> Francis; <hi>the Medals of the Fourth Sts. or</hi> Borromie, <hi>the holy Water and Exorciſms with Salt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>I Believe Diſpenſation for a certain Price, the cruel Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, the giving of Kingdoms to the firſt Uſurper, the Maſſacre of all thoſe who withſtand the Court of</hi> Rome, <hi>the Eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe who ſtray from his Commands, and an infernal Curſe upon all thoſe who (without any Reſerve) do not obey all his Orders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>I Believe, that if one ſhoud know that if the Pope did neglect his own Salvation and that of his Brethren, if he ſhould lead multitudes with him without Number to Damnation to be ſlaves of Hell, no Mortal could, without preſumption, reprehend his Faults, becauſe he who judges all others, cannot be Judged by any one. See the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals in</hi> 4. <hi>Diſtinct. Canon.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>I Believe generally that the Romane Church only and thoſe who obey her in all things without Contradiction and reſerve, are</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques <hi>and</hi> Apoſtoliques.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>I Believe alſo the new Morality of the Jeſuits favoured by the Pope, and the Doctrine of</hi> Vernant <hi>and that of the</hi> Guimeneus, <hi>whoſe Condemnation made by</hi> Sorbon, <hi>hath been burnt as an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique by an expreſs Bull from the Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>I believe that there is as well Piety as juſtice in the crimes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, tolerated, and allowed on by the Pope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>I Believe generally that Chriſt and the Pope have but one and the ſame Power and Tribunal, and that all Power is given to him in Heaven and Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58669:23"/>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>In a Word, I Believe that one ought to follow, in ſpight of what ever can be ſaid the ſine conceits of the Cardinal of</hi> Perroon, <hi>in reſpect of Pope</hi> Clement <hi>the Eighth of whom he held his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I Have always Reverenc'd your Bleſſedneſs as a God upon Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Creed</hi> is very long, and much more than that of which the firſt Chriſtians made Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>If this <hi>Creed</hi> divides all Chriſtianity, if it hinders the Peace of our hearts in <hi>France;</hi> Let us all beſeech our Gracious King to Stand, and make us Stand alſo to the <hi>Creed</hi> of that Generous <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> and of ſo many Excellent Biſhops, the moſt part of whom bore the marks of Martyrdom, which they received during the Perſecution.</p>
               <p>O how happy ſhould we be, if we had nothing elſe to do, but to obey God and the King; how contented would our lives be and how quiet our Conſciences, if the King would give us Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and Liberty not to change the Incorruptible Glory of God into the Image of Corruptible Man; how Contented and Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous would his Majeſty be, if he would Unite all of us by the Truth of God, ſince that we are not divided but by the Vanity of Man.</p>
               <p n="32">32. Although the Roman-Catholiques are tyed by Cuſtom to their Ceremonies, which makes Religion to be a ſhew; although they glory much in their Profeſſion, ſeeing themſelves upheld, and the Proteſtants low in the preſent ſtate of affairs; although Cuſtom makes them imagine, the Religion of the Proteſtants in <hi>France</hi> at too far a diſtance from that which pleaſeth the phancy &amp; ſence of the People; Yet it is certain, if they had taſted the good Word, and found without fear and prejudice the Eſſence of true Piety, they would reliſh it with Pleaſure and Comfort, they would approve of that holy Truth which the Prophet ſpoke, <hi>Taſt &amp; ſee how ſweet the Lord is;</hi> they would rebuke with ſcorn an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite company of Follies, which they dare neither leave nor cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in their preſent condition.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58669:24"/>
               <p>I have ſeen more than a hundred perſons of great Quality, whoſe Souls were above the Vulgar, laugh at, or bemoan theſe Superſtitious Actions and low Opinions which the Vulgar made their dear Devotions, and which many Hypocritical Cheats would make go for conſiderable matters.</p>
               <p>Mounſ. <hi>Abbot</hi> Marreau of <hi>Ville-Loing</hi> ſhews in all his writings that he had a great Soul when he ſpeaks moſt generouſly of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Heads attributed to St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and of the Blood of Chriſt kept in glaſſes, and of many other low things, which ſtuff the Devotion, and daub it with Mud or Ink; ſo I call the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures of the Bablers of Fables, and the Writers of Prodigies: I have heard many of the beſt ſort of Eccleſiaſtiques, ſay, that they ſuffered much violence to comply with, and follow ſuch groſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes to their Senſe and Knowledg; but becauſe Contradiction or neglect paſſed for a Crime in regard of the received uſe, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that they acted like wiſe men, when they trifled and play'd the Fools like the Ignorant: I can aſſure you, <hi>Eutimius,</hi> that the diſtance which I perceive for the particular Creed of the Pope, which is explained here, doth not come from a prejudiced mind, but from a ſincere heart, which doth not ſuffer me to commit my Salvation and my Faith to <hi>Ideas,</hi> where I remarque weakneſs &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certitude; I ſpeak in reſpect of thoſe who believe them, for thoſe who do not, have ſpirit and underſtanding to manage their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, laughing at theſe ridiculous Weakneſſes.</p>
               <p>Many generous Souls brought up in the Romiſh Communion, have the ſame thoughts that I have, although they have not the ſame which animate me; they have too many knots to break or untye; they are content only to ſlack them, they ſee to cut them aſunder, is an offence againſt the publique Opinion.</p>
               <p>Certain of my Friends ſpeaking to me of this matter, tell me that a Wiſe man ſeldom takes up that Reſolution which his Maſter blames, and his Companions hate.</p>
               <p>In ſpite of the Cuſtom of ſome, and the Policy of others, if his Majeſty would determine, to make the Star of Freedom
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58669:24"/>ſhine, he would quickly ſee the day of Unity; all hearts and minds would willingly render themſelves to the Truth of God, Countenanced by the King; and all eyes love light, although they are not Priſoners; ſo all that are Generous and Rational in <hi>France,</hi> would joyn without noiſe and without trouble to true Reaſon and noble Piety; no one can reſiſt the loving force of that which is Good, Fair, and True.</p>
               <p n="33">33. When his Majeſty teſtifies his deſire of the Agreement of his Subjects, he wiſhes firſt the Glory of God, and then the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and honour of that Church, which bears the title of the <hi>French Church;</hi> are we not all obliged by the Zeal of our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and for the Intereſt of our moſt dear Country, to carry our Affections highly towards his Majeſties deſign? let us procure the Glory of God, and the happineſs of the Church of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the firſt, let us not be ſo weak and erroneous to believe that the Honour of God is increaſed when that of <hi>Rome</hi> is; the Authority of the King, who is a Sacred Majeſty, is ſufficient to make us Preach, Underſtand, and Obſerve the Will of God; for the ſecond are we ſo baſe to ſeek after with an unnatural Zeal the glory of the Roman Court, to the prejudice of the French Church?</p>
               <p>The Gentlemen of <hi>Sorbon</hi> making their Cenſures or judicious Obſervations on <hi>Odoricus Renaldus,</hi> Continuer of <hi>Baronius,</hi> have branded as notable faults that which is writ againſt the French Church and its Liberty. Theſe Liberties are not Licentiouſneſs, but, as the Wiſe learnedly explain, an exact Obſervation of the Ancient Rules of the Chriſtian Faith.</p>
               <p>Would to God that all the Kings Subjects, upon this occaſion, had the love to hold themſelves to the Rules of that Faith which is called Canons; and ten or twelve Perſons of each Religion, had the Command to ſearch them, not in Modern Antiquity, but Apoſtolique, and in that of the firſt Councils; they would eaſily find the French Liberty well eſtabliſhed, and the Dependence on <hi>Rome</hi> very ill-founded.</p>
               <p>I ask if our French Church can be unjuſt, if ſhe takes the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58669:25"/>demanded by 5 Embaſſadours of <hi>France,</hi> in ſeveral Reductions of the Council of <hi>Trent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Would ſhe not be as holy when ſhe Regulates her Faith upon Divine words, and her Manners upon the Sacred Laws of God, as though ſhe ſerved the Statues of the Grandeur of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Cardinal of <hi>Lorain,</hi> did not he do a greater Service to the French Church when he endeavoured a Reformation in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> than by that baſe Compliance which he had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to the Will of the Pope.</p>
               <p>Are not the Gentlemen of <hi>Sorbon</hi> generous and Chriſtian, when ſpeaking of the works of <hi>Renaldus,</hi> they ſay that the French-Church hath done nothing more profitable than the Pragmatick Sanction, which Sanction was made at <hi>Burges,</hi> in the year 1438. The King Aſſembled Biſhops, Princes, and the great Lords of his Kingdom; but becauſe it bound the Authority of the Pope, it was looked upon as a black attempt, and that was it which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it praiſe-worthy.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty may if he pleaſe do ſomthing better, he may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the great Remedy to the Malady, which hath broken our bones, and eaten our fleſh; whereas others have ordered nothing but Lenitives, and applyed them with a trembling hand.</p>
               <p>Let us deſire (my dear <hi>Eutimius</hi>) let us deſire this holy Unity of one and the ſame Religion; his Majeſty who wiſheth it, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires our common good; 'tis an evil thing to hate, as 'tis an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happineſs to be hated.</p>
               <p>The thoughts which I have newly explained to you, ſhall end with this, we ſhould be happy if we had but one God in Heaven, and one Monarch upon Earth.</p>
               <p>I beſeech the Almighty to inſpire the King not to permit in his Kingdom a Companion with God; and that he would propoſe ways to us, which are only drawn from the Law and Truth of God, to be the Rule of our Devotions; his Majeſty will acquire Glory in giving us Peace; <hi>France</hi> will have all the Properties of being the One, the True and the Good, and we ſhall have Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Soul, Truth in Spirit, and Unity of hearts.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:58669:25"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
